how to make a practice out of reflect
incorrectly it's it does a lot of it
come down to repetition and drilling so
going through the not necessarily just
to the motion you might have to start
but going through emotions but really
which can also be done even even for
reflection that's what happens to people
sometimes initially you establish your
mind upon certain reflexive attitude
about certain contexts or a topic but
then afterwards you just want to almost
like have a shortcut to it and then just
go through the mental motions and expect
the same establishment but needless to
say it doesn't it doesn't work or it
stops working that's when you know that
your practice became mechanical and
that's when you either have to shift up
the approach or again we include your
attempts at the shortcut into the
present situation so in other words if
say for example the context of your
establishment of the mind is mind above
sensuality and you want to be always
starting any any reflection for that
matter doesn't matter the context as
much as a topic you're trying to
contemplate you want to be doing it on
the basis of the presently enduring
situation so right here right now but
you don't just say oh I'm right here
right now as a matter of fact you you
have to that kind of recognition needs
to be rooted in how you feel right here
right now
because as the Buddha said things
converge on the level of feeling so and
that's exactly when you practice or
meditation becomes mechanical it's when
it's not rooted in how you're feeling
presently how when it's not rooted in
the presently enduring feeling that's
the accurate way of putting so how are
you feeling right now and if the context
as I said if
this is the practice of establishing the
mind above the domain of sensuality
based on the currently enduring feeling
it's a neutral feeling or say it's
pleasant feeling as in pleasant as a
good mood so you want to again as a good
often encourage you to review your mind
not necessarily psychologically analyze
it just stay on the level of the
presently enduring feeling that's
enduring there on its own for this whole
time now and then you want to review
your mind in a sense of c4c and
reconsider whether us.we whether you
would be liable that a dead mind would
be liable to sensual desire or to
ill-will because those things are on the
same domain so you can you can you can
simply ask yourself that question so
right here right now while I'm sitting
in this room having a pleasant mood
enduring so that's the test the
establishment of the situation based on
the what present feeling in doors you
don't need to rush for the answer as I
often say so allow this situation to
endure don't miss the fight but
certainly don't try to provide answers
for it if you have any doubts so now
there's doubt you can ask well am I
still feeling a positive or a good good
two neutral mood whichever you want to
describe it and if the answer is yes
means the same mood is still enduring so
that's that's the important in important
bit to to discern and then allowed to do
so then even you doubt is secondary to
how you're feeling right here right now
again if you're not rooted at the point
where things convert which is at the
point of present enduring feeling that's
when doubt can take over you but as I
said you just have to really include it
include doubt in the president indirect
feeling and even if it's unpleasant then
you surmount it by by being mindful of
the of the feeling that step beforehand
pretty much because you're doubting your
mood only because that mood is
who you doubting how you might be
feeling because you must be feeling
something so so in the specific context
of establishing mind about sensuality
even temporarily so to speak you have to
aim at establishing your mind above the
possibility of sensuality and that
already means that you have been living
certainly for a sufficient amount of
time certainly invested sufficient
amount of effort living withdrawn from
sensuality bodily so if if your eggs are
not withdrawn from sensuality bodily as
in if there is no virtue basis of virtue
and basis of sensitive strained and you
you're not going to be discerning
anything of there any of this on the
level of the mind so that's why the the
virtue needs to come first
your sila the precepts is not the Dharma
but there is no damage without it and
this is exactly why you cannot possibly
discern the liability to sensuality on
the mental level when you are fully
immersed in it physically or certainly
when you haven't been withdrawn from it
long enough physically so taking for
granted that you have been withdrawn
long enough physically as in you have
been keeping the precepts then you are
creating a certain well to an extent
some some degree a degree of a basis for
this discernment and the sermon is as
follows you just ask yourself on the
basis of present enduring feeling am I
liable to sense desire as in is this
mind this present enduring is currently
positive Pleasant feeling is he liable
to be sort of taken up by central clay
gripped by it under the pressure of
sensual desire if you are not sure means
it is so not being clear that you are
free from it to that extent you are not
free from it so you can review the
possibility and that's all it was in
Charlotte it is by the way you don't
need to be reviewing possibility and
then waiting for sensuality
come there is no sensuality to the
sensuality stays on the level of
possibility or others begins already on
the level of possibility so if you deal
with it over there then you wouldn't
have to be dealing only on the level of
physical and senses because possibility
to sensual desire is already sensuality
it's already essential desire so that's
what I mentioned in other talks you can
imagine a possibility of sensual
engagement and that's already where your
gratification begins begins on the level
of the thought of of the prospect of
central engagement or the prospect that
is actually unpleasant because if the
prospect of sensual engagement were
already Pleasant felt pleasantly at the
end the fundamental primal level the
desire to words what that prospect
directs you would be inconceivable
because you're already within the
satisfied pleasure but that's the whole
point it's felt unpleasantly and it
directs you in a direction toward sense
object they will make this
unpleasantness less we felt less and
that's why people end up developing a
gojira's assumption that that which you
get down that direction is pleasant but
it isn't it's just slightly less
unpleasant but it's equally within the
same unpleasantness and the important
point here to start seeing this
direction is to recognize that first you
start with sense of pleasure so for a
mind that's not free from sensuality you
cannot possibly see it as unpleasant
first and then you can sort of an
emulate seeing of that and that's that's
a good way to that's that's an
inevitable way to start but the point is
factually speaking on the basis of your
present enduring experience as a whole
sensuality is felt pleasantly that's the
first step so that's why it's important
to practice sense restraint because if
you're not allowed if you if you're not
able to allow the that pleasure to
manifest for what it is you won't be
able to see it and by not being able to
allow pleasure pleasure to manifest for
what it is means not having practice
sense restraint sufficiently
or well enough so as soon as this
pleasure start the prospect of this
pleasure starts to increase you're bound
to give in so again that's where Cielo
needs to be developed first so that you
can then allow this thing to arise and
then understand it for what it is see
the pain in it inherent the heart of it
is always painful cannot be different so
you would be able to allow that if you
haven't been habitually automatically
carelessly acting on the level of the
physical based on the desire so
basically if you haven't been given in
to to sensuality on the level of your
body if you are able to allow that
pleasure that's felt first it's then
within the basis of that enduring
prospect of pleasure which is pleasant
within that basis you get to understand
the pressure that the fundamental exerts
on you and you can ask yourself you
being pressured is that Pleasant or
unpleasant it's always unpleasant always
unpleasant so within the play presently
enduring pleasure of the prospect of
sensuality you get to understand that
it's always fundamentally felt painfully
and that's the important thing
for as long as you assume even to the
tiniest of the degrees that pleasure of
the prospect of sensuality is in the
direction of these sense objects even
tiny little bit more then it's on the
level of the present enduring painful
pressure that it exists over you to that
extent you assume it to be different to
that extent you give it its own being
being of sensuality as in being that
pertains to over that that thing over
there that is being promised as the
object of your sense so that's why once
you're able to allow that pleasure try
so you mustn't be I must get rid of this
I must get rid of this and you certainly
mustn't be giving in physically once
you're able to allow it to endure you
will see that the pleasure that you feel
of that endurance is actually the pain
of its pressure it's the same thing
literally just the other coin of the
same thing and at that point it would be
thing and at that point it would be
impossible for you to regard that
prospect of pleasure is anything other
than painful and that's exactly what the
Buddha described in the in dessert as we
mentioned in previous talks as well
imagine melikhaya the point being
engagement with sin suffering was always
actually unpleasant always so and you
will know that it was always unpleasant
because again ask yourself can you even
conceive going down the direction of a
sense object pursuing it engaging with
it
using it for gratification if there is
no desire for it so the context of your
engagement with sense object is always
the desire of the sense always it's in
consumer because if you engage with the
sense object without the desire for the
sense object that's not sensuality
that's not an engagement there is no
last an aversion basis for lust an
aversion in it so that's that's why you
recognize the context peripheral context
of your presently directed mind toward
sense object is always unpleasant
pressure of that sense desire so if that
is the inevitable inseparable
unremovable irremovable context of any
central direction means any central
direction is then that which pressures
you because of which it's painful so
it's important to not create a
distinction as I said temporal
distinction of given spatial distinction
for the matter between the pleasure that
you feel first on the prospect of
sensuality and the underlying inherent
pressure it exerts over you which is the
pain so then the prospect of pleasure is
directly determined by the prospect of
pressure exerted over you in other words
pleasure you feel it's actually the pain
that pressures you and the reason you
feel it Pleasant is because the
direction offered is the direction of
possible escape from it so that again
imagine that like you're imprisoned you
you've been tortured and suddenly a
thought occurs in your mind that allows
a possibility of escape from the torture
now the possibility of escape from the
present hindering exerted torture over
you if that possibility is slim well
you're not going to get very elated it's
gonna be but yeah but imagine that
possibility being really quite realistic
well you will you will you will have
trouble containing your excitement and
that's exactly the definition of
sensuality when it comes down to senses
imprisoned by the desire that then
determines the extent of pleasure you
will feel as in a the extent of possible
escape from it so the greater the desire
the greater possibility of escape and
thus for the inner mind the greater
pleasure so that's why I mean you have
to admit that there is this great
pleasure or medium pleasure pleasure is
there once you admit you will get to see
that pleasure is felt pleasantly because
it's determined by the pain in other
words you've the pain is felt pleasantly
the underlying pain the peripheral pain
the context of pain is felt pleasantly
because you're looking away from it and
that's again that's exactly in the suit
that we quote quoted before the Buddha
said it was that gave a similar of the
leper and using the burning embers to
cauterize his scratching bone that
offers him a sense of relief and he said
they would have said the fire and
burning embers were always painful Orbis
the only reason that he was finding it
pleasurable genuinely otherwise he
wouldn't be doing it in the first place
a leper would not have been going to the
embers if they were not providing him at
least some degree of pleasure but it
would have said that pleasure was always
actually painful the only reason he was
finding a relief in it delighting in it
being happy on account of it was because
of his condition of leprosy that's it
and condition of life precedes the
condition of ignorance in regard to your
own sensuality in regard to your own
pressure of the sense desire because
once the leper learns that the first
thing he must do
in order to cure his leprosy stop
scratching it and stop burning it with
fire then he'll get to realize that yeah
that truly is the way out so sense
destroy must be first and then you get
to understand it if I used to do what
you used to do when I count of escaping
from sensuality was actually just making
sensuality voice because you were just
by being pressure from pain that you
were feeling pleasantly you were causing
yourself even more pain that I was then
felt even more pleasantly that was
making you cause even more pain that was
being felt even more pleasantly
that's why sensuality is endless this
you can't satisfy your desires and you
certainly will never run out of
preferences the mind will always keep
pushing further and further and further
if that's the direction it goes and it
can go infinitely because that's not
direction with the desires up yet as I
said any engagement resent object is on
account of you not wanting sense desire
to be there so once you realize that
always whenever there is a sense desire
there was always a criteria of not
wanting it and that's a good criteria
it's just then choosing how you go about
it that's what determines it what is
gonna be sensuality or not so any sense
desire is not wanted because it's
unpleasant cause it's pressure if you
give in towards it trying to alleviate
that pain through distracting yourself
with sensual pursuit you're making it
worse if you don't go towards it you
might increase the pain initially
because as I said the leper does get a
degree of relief from scratching and
burning it with fire so once he stops
engaging with that degree of relief the
things are gonna go worse but they're
gonna start healing and that's the point
here healing means you start to
understand that doesn't matter how tiny
prospect of pleasure arises in your mind
if is directly the senses you know it's
because it's painful that's why it's
pleasure because it's painful because it
pressures you thus the escape of it is
pleasant only because of the pressure
would you be elated at escaping the
torture chamber if you're not imprisoned
there if you can come and go as you
leave you wouldn't there would be no
delight at the prospect of escape
because you are not imprisoned by it so
that's exactly what I mean the genuine
pleasure that sensuality offers even
actually while you're amidst of physical
engagement with sensuality the happiness
of it the joy the pleasure is the
pleasure of pain felt on the level of
the same things being present
so the happiness of sensuality is
because of the painful presence of the
same sensuality it's the same thing just
two different directions and you keep
choosing to look at the direction they
distracts you from it that's why we like
we keep insisting on the developing
mindfulness of the peripheral in the
context because this is all found in the
context as I said you start with a
thought of sensuality what is the
context of it well it's the peripheral
enduring context of desire for that now
you get to discern the peripheral
enduring context of the desire for this
particular sense then you also get to
this in further peripheral what are the
characteristics of the present enduring
pressuring desire to do to eat something
will touch something or smell something
of both pleasant nature well the fact is
that it's it's it's pressuring you
unpleasantly always can you be pressured
pleasantly and then go and seek the
escape from me no why would you do that
there's nothing to escape from so you
were pressured by the pain of it that is
then like as I said inherent context of
any sensual direction
so you will be going down to sensuality
because you want to avoid pain so then
you dress okay I want to avoid pain
that's absolutely fine what is the best
way of going about it
going down sexuality clearly keeps
making it worse what if I were to
restrain so so the mind can have a
chance to develop in regard to this
pressure and is not pressure by it
anymore when the mind is not pressured
by the prospect of sensuality the mind
is not wealth the mind has surmounted
the domain of sensuality so that's we
come back to how we started how to
contemplate how to develop mind they
would say mount the the domain of
sensualities develop the mind that
cannot be pressured by the possibility
of sensuality in other words develop the
mind they will always be able to quickly
instantaneously simply
tenuously this central reason thought is
pain and then he won't go near it
you won't even have to they make the
effort to not go near it he won't go
near it and that's again what the Buddha
will describe by the the leper who is
now healed his leprosy and his wounds he
said why imagine now that he's healed
skin normally covered and our two strong
men come and pick him up and try to
carry him back into those burning embers
wouldn't he resist and kick and scream
and like think anything else except
going into the embassy yes of course he
would so that's exactly the point even
the slightest thought that the factual
presence of possibility of sensuality
right in your face
access to the central object will be
pain access to pain and the mind will
shock like completely completely shiver
away from it it's just it will not even
come entertain it for a second because
if he does it that any for a second
means that second it still thinks it's
present first not unpleasant first if
it's unpleasant first and the pleasure
of it can never step outside of the
context of the pain means that pleasure
is not pleasure is just distraction from
pain which is felt pleasantly only
because of the perspective of the pain
greater pain so that's it you maintain
the context you maintain the mind above
sensuality and mind above will will for
that matter because your will is equally
directional somebody something upsets
you that's already unpleasant what you
do you want to get rid of the impression
are you getting rid of the displeasure
by attacking that which upset you but if
you realize that you cannot possibly be
upset by that which comes through the
sense objects you can only be upset by
resisting the pressure of that which
comes to the sense objects now you stop
resisting it means yeah as the Buddha
said you can literally endure sticks and
stones abuse verbal abuse physical abuse
and the mind will be incapable of anger
not like you have to keep it free from
anger it will be incapable from anger
because anger is painful
sticks and stones are not painful
objects of your senses are just
agreeable or disagreeable they're not
from the level of pain and suffering
however you being pressured by
the possibility of escaping anger that's
what you're suffering it you being
pressured by the possibility of escape
in the pain of sensual desire that's
where the suffering is that's why these
things are always underlined by the
inherent craving for getting rid of it
getting rid of the sensual desire cause
it's unpleasant getting rid of the pain
because it's again it's unpleasant
sorry getting rid of the aversion pain
of a version because it's unpleasant so
you've given to anger you give to
central object you give in to the
offered direction of less pain failing
to see that less pain is still pain more
pain less pain shares the nature of pain
but yes if you forget that and start
looking well as long as I avoid greater
pain for the sake of less pain then less
pain will be regarded as pleasure and
the extent of the pleasure is basically
the extent to the pain that underlines
it